Ernst Bacon Papers
Ernst Bacon Papers
1917-1991
Bacon, Ernst, 1898-1990.
27 linear ft.
Papers of the American composer, pianist, and conductor; Director of School of Music, Syracuse University and professor (1945-1963). Manuscripts, notebooks, sketchbooks, photographs, printed music, and essays. Notable correspondents in the collection inlude Ansel Adams, Carlisle Floyd, John Alden Carpenter, Kay Boyle, Aaron Copland, Witter Bynner, and Van Wyck Brooks.
150232
Biographical History
Ernst Bacon (1898-1990) was an American composer, pianist, conductor, chamber musician, and teacher. For much of his teaching career he was Director of the School of Music at Syracuse University.
Born in Chicago, May 26, 1898, the son of Dr. Charles S. and Maria von Rosthorn Bacon, he attended Northwestern University and the University of Chicago, but obtained his master's degree from the University of California in 1935. He studied in Vienna for a time. After his return, He was associated with the Rochester Opera Company. Later he became conductor of the San Francisco Orchestra of the Federal Music Project, 1935-1937.
His first academic appointment was as acting professor of music at Hamilton College, in New York. Later he became Dean of the School of Music at Converse College, Spartanburg, South Carolina, 1938-1945. Mr. Bacon was appointed Director of the School of Music at Syracuse University in 1945, where he also taught piano and composition. In 1947 he became composer-in-residence. In Sept. 1964, he became composer-in-residence at the University of California at Berkley.
Mr. Bacon's major compositions were a musical play, A Drumlin Legend, commissioned by the Ditson Fund and premiered at the Columbia University Festival of Contemporary Music; his orchestral suite, From These States, in eleven movements, performed by the NBC Symphony; and his folk opera, A Tree on the Plains, commissioned originally by the League of Composers in 1940, had its premier at the Spartanburg, S.C., Festival, and which received the David Bispham Award for Contemporary Opera, Chicago 1946.
Mr. Bacon was awarded the Pulitzer Fellowship in 1932; Guggenheim Fellowship in 1939, 1942, Campion Citation; Grant-Citation National Institute of Arts and Letters; and he wrote musical criticism for the New York Times as well as musical commentary for the Syracuse Post-Standard and the Berkley Gazette. He is the author of the book Words on Music.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ernst Bacon Papers consists of three separate accessions. The researcher is advised to explore the entire inventory to ensure locating all relevant material.
Main collection
The main collection consists of four series: correspondence, musical manuscripts, literary manuscripts, and published material.
Correspondence is arranged chronologically, apart from a few notable correspondents foldered separately. Notable correspondents in the chronological material inlude John Alden Carpenter, Kay Boyle, Aaron Copland, Witter Bynner, and Van Wyck Brooks.
Manuscripts is subdivided into material relating to Songs from Emily Dickinson, material relating to A Tree on the Plains, and general music scores. Material relating to Songs from Emily Dickinson and A Tree on the Plains is further subdivided into bound and unbound manuscripts; this in turn is further broken down into the types of manuscripts, such as orchestral, piano, songs, et cetera. General music scores is arranged by type or instrument for which the music was written (Cello & piano, choral, contrapuntal studies, opera, orchestral, piano, sketch books, sketches, and songs) and within that, alphabetically by title. When several scores were bound together or appeared in folio form, the title of the first piece was used for an alphabetical arrangement.
Literary manuscripts consists of addresses (radio), articles, books and plays, arranged alphabetically by title. All but one are typescript, although Bacon's handwritten corrections appear on many of the typescripts.
Published materials consists of articles, booklets, clippings and so on about and by Ernst Bacon. Material is subdivided by type.
Additions: University Archives
Two separate groupings of material were transferred from University Archives in 1991. The first grouping consists of Compositions and Writings. The second grouping consists of Artwork, Compositions, Writings, and Memorabilia (awards and photographs).
The bulk of this material remains in original order as received, and therefore is not consistently arranged. Some of this material duplicates items in other parts of the collection.
Additions: Don Siebert
A small amount of material, consisting of various scores and one essay, was donated to the collection in 1993 by Don Siebert, who was for more than forty years the Music Librarian for Syracuse University Libraries. Some of this material duplicates items in other parts of the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
See Scope and content note above.
Related Material
has the papers of several important composers and musicians, including Franz Waxman and Miklos Rozsa. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Music; New York State; Bacon, Ernst, 1898-1990.; Composers -- United States.; Conductors (Music) -- United States.; Music -- 20th century.; Musicians -- United States.; Orchestral music -- Scores and parts.; Pianists -- United States.; Songs with orchestra -- Vocal scores with piano.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Essays.; Manuscripts for publication.; Musical scores.; Photographs.; Composers.; Conductors (Music).; Musicians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Adams, Ansel, 1937-1938; undated (Box 1)
  - Floyd, Carlisle, 1946-1967 (Box 1)
  - Letters to editors, 1940-1949; undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1925-1991; some notable (Box 1)
- Manuscripts, musical
  - Songs from Emily Dickinson
    - Bound copy of Songs, Second Series (Oversize 1)
      Contains the following:
      "As If Some Little Artic Flower" (original), 3 pages
      "Come Slowly, Eden!" (original), 3 pages
      "How Happy Is the Little Stone" (original), 2 pages
      "So Well That I Can Live Without" (original), 1 page
      "Oh, Shadow on the Grass" (original), 2 pages
      "It's All I Have" (original), 2 pages
      "Poor Little Heart" (original), 2 pages
      "Today or This Noon" (original), 1 page
      "The Cricket Sang" (original), 4 pages
      "And This of All My Hopes" (original), 2 pages
      "There Came a Wind Like a Bugle" (original), 5 pages
      "I Felt a Funeral in My Brain" (original), 4 pages
      "The Grass" (revised), 3 pages
      "So Set Its Sun in Thee" (original), 2 pages
      "So Bashful When I Spied Her" original), 2 pages
      "There Is a Solitude of Space" (original), 2 pages
      Bound with this is a copy of Songs From Emily Dickinson, 36 pages, which contains 12 songs (As if the sea should part, From blank to blank, Savior, How still the bells, The grass has so little to do, She went as quiet as the dew, My river runs to thee, I'm nobody, Let down the bars, It's coming the postponeless creature, The sun went down, Wild nights, The heart asks pleasure first)
    - Unbound copies (Oversize 1)
      Folio, containing "It's All I Have to Bring Today" et al. (original), 3 pages; The Sun Went Down" et al. (original), 4 pages
      Single copies of the following:
      "Alter?" (original), 2 pages
      "And This of All My Hopes" (original), 1 page
      "As If the Sea Should Part" (original), 1 page
      "From Blank to Blank" (original), 1 page
      "The Grass So Little Has to Do" (original), 3 pages
      "The Heart Asks Pleasure First" (original), 3 pages
      "How Still the Bells" (original), 2 pages
      "It's Coming - The Postponeless Creature" (original and revised), 5 pages
      "It's Such a Little Thing (original)
      "Savior" 1930 (original), 3 pages
      "Savior" III (original), 3 pages
      "Savior" May 1930 (original), 2 pages
      "She Went As Quiet As the Dew" (original) (Seite/95), 2 pages
      "She Went As Quiet As the Dew" Oct. 1930 (original), 2 pages
      "A Spider" (original), 1 page
      "The Sun Went Down" (original), 2 pages
      "Today or This Noon" (original), 2 pages
      "With the First Arbutus" (original)
      "A Word" (reproduction), 1 page
      Sketch: "For Emily's Diary" (published by G. Schirmer) (original), 36 pages
  - A Tree on the Plains
    - Bound copy, dialogue and stage directions (reproduction), 5 copies (Box 1)
    - Scores
      - Full Score, 2 volumes (Oversize 2)
        Volume I (reproduction), 138 pages
        Volume II (reproduction), 120 pages
      - Parts, orchestral (Box 2)
        Bass I (reproduction), 48 pages
        Bass II (reproduction), 48 pages
        Celesta (reproduction), typescript, 8 pages
        Cello (reproduction), 53 pages, 2 copies
        Clarinet I (reproduction), 39 pages
        Clarinet II (reproduction), 27 pages
        Fagott (reproduction), 32 pages
        Flute Alternating with Piccolo, 35 pages
        Harp (reproduction), 28 pages
        Horn I in F (reproduction), 29 pages
        Horn II in F (reproduction), 25 pages
        Oboe- Alternate with English Horn (reproduction), 31 pages
        Percussion - Bells and Xylophone (reproduction), 41 pages
        Percussion - Vibbs (reproduction), 41 pages, 2 copies
        Piano (reproduction), 45 pages
      - Parts, orchestral (cont.) (Box 3)
        Timpani (reproduction), 13 pages
        Trombone I (reproduction), 20 pages
        Trombone II (reproduction), 19 pages
        Trumpet I (reproduction), 28 pages
        Trumpet II (reproduction), 20 pages
        Tuba (reproduction), 20 pages
        Viola (reproduction), 49 pages, 2 copies
        Violin I (reproduction), 53 pages, 4 copies
        Violin II (reproduction) some original, 41 pages, 2 copies
      - Parts, orchestral (cont.) (Oversize 2)
        Piano and Voice (reproduction), 159 pages
    - Unbound copies
      - Orchestral, full score, folio, original version (Oversize 3)
        "Lou" (original and rep.), 9 pages
        "Love O'Clock" (original and rep.), 14 pages
        "Pop's Greeting" (original and rep.), 5 pages
        "The Jeremiah and Pop's Sermon" (original and rep.), 35 pages
        "The Last Train" (original and rep.), 13 pages
        "Just Let It Be" (original and rep.), 20 pages
        "Heat of the Plains" (original and rep.), 4 pages
        "Tough Cookie" (original and rep.), 11 pages
        "The Flower Patch" (original and rep.), 2 pages
        "Conversation Before a Storm" (original and rep.), 2 pages
        "Chewing Gum Island" (original and rep.), 13 pages
        "Night-time Music" (original and rep.), 10 pages
        "Buddy", 4 pages
        "Hey" (original and rep.), 11 pages
        "The Coming of Rain" (original and rep.), 17 pages
        "Frog Went A Courtin'" (original and rep.), 19 pages
        "Hymn to Evening" (original and rep.), 6 pages
        "Lou and Corrie" (original and rep.), 27 pages
        "Stars and Moon" (original and rep.), 21 pages
        "The Vamoose" (original and rep.), 8 pages
        "Pop's Song" (original and rep.), 12 pages
        "The Philosopher" (original and rep.), 7 pages
        "The Colorado Trail" (original and rep.), 20 pages
      - Piano, first version, folio (Oversize 2)
        "Stirrings of Air" (original), 1 page
        "A Pantomime of the Returning Neighbors" (original), 5 pages
        "Lou" (original), 2 pages
        "Lou and Corrie" (original), 6 pages
        "Love O'Clock" (original), 6 pages
        "Twenty Miles" (original) 4 pages
        "Pop's Greeting" (original) 4 pages
        "The Jeremiah and Pop's Sermon" (original), 25 pages
        "Mom" (original), 13 pages
        "The Last Train" (original), 8 pages
        "Just Let It Be" (original), 11 pages
        "Heat of the Plains" (original), 6 pages
        "Buddy" (original), 1 page
        "Tough Cookie" (original), 19 pages
        "Chewing Gum Island" (original), 13 pages
        "The Fight" (original), 22 pages
        "The Rain Pours Down Nightly" (original), 14 pages
        "Transport Plane" (original), 12 pages
        "Vamp for Froggie" (original), 1 page
        "Froggie" (original), 25 pages
        "Hymn to Evening" (original), 9 pages
        "Corrie's Song" (original), 7 pages
        "Duet- Lou and Corrie" (original), 19 pages
        "The Reverend" (original), 1 page
        "Of Stars and the Moon" (original), 15 pages
        "The Vamoose" (original), 11 pages
        "Moonset" (original), 35 pages
        "Corrie's Song" (original), 6 pages
      - Piano, incomplete version, folio (Oversize 2)
        "Fit To Be Tied" (original), 10 pages
        "Song of the Little Tree" (original), 2 pages
        "Twenty Miles" (original), 2 pages
        "The Jeremiah and Sermon" (original), 14 pages
        "The Progress of Streams" (original), 10 pages
        "Dialogue: Lou & Corrie" (original), 1 page
        "The Jeremiah and Pop's Sermon" (original), 10 pages
        "Let It Be" (original), 3 pages
        "Let It Be" (original), 5 pages
        "The Way It Is In Town" (original), 1 page
        "Heat of the Plains" (original), 4 pages
        "Night-time Music" (original), 4 pages
        "Conversation Before a Storm" (original), 5 pages
        "Chewing Gum Island" (original), 2 pages
        "The Coming of Rain" (original), 6 pages
        "Buddy" (original), 2 pages
        "Hymn to Evening"(original), 2 pages
        "Sequel to Hymn" (original), 1 page
        "Recitative, Blues, and Arioso" (original), 12 pages
        "Forever" (original), 8 pages
        "The Philosopher" (original)
      - Songs, folio bound copies (Oversize 4)
        "Frog A Courtin'" et al. (reproduction), 11 pages
        "Heat of the Plains" (reproduction), 4 pages
        "The Last Train" (reproduction), 5 pages, 2 copies
        "Lou" et al. (reproduction), 40 pages, 2 copies
        "Lou" (reproduction), 3 pages
        "Lou's Discourse" (reproduction), 1 page
        "Lou's Song" (reproduction), 4 pages
        "Mom" (reproduction), 3 pages
        "Mom and Corrie" (reproduction), 3 pages
        "Mom and Pop" (reproduction), 3 pages
        "Morning After the Rain" (reproduction), 4 pages
        "Pop's Greeting" (reproduction), 4 pages
        "Pop's Sermon" (reproduction), 5 pages
        "Prelude" et al. (reproduction), 3 pages
        "Rain Jubilation" (reproduction), 3 pages
        "Tough Cookie" et al. (reproduction), 20 pages
        "Twenty Miles" et al. (original and reproduction), 13 pages, 3 copies
        "Wind Before the Rain" et al. (original and reproduction), 4 pages
      - Songs, single copies (Oversize 4)
        "About Mom" (reproduction), 4 pages
        "About Mom" (original), 3 pages
        "About Mom" (reproduction), 1 page
        "Amen Chorus" (reproduction), 2 pages, 10 copies
        "Amen Chorus" (original and reproduction), 2 pages
        "Before the Rain" (original), 2 pages
        "Buddy's Nocturne" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "Chewing Gum Island" (reproduction), 5 pages, 2 copies
        "Chewing Gum Island" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "The Coming of Rain" (original), 2 pages
        "Corrie" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "Corrie" (reproduction), 1 page
        "The Fight" (reproduction), 1 page, 12 copies
        "Finale" (rep,.), 1 page
        "Frog A Courtin" (reproduction), 10 pages, 4 copies
        "Greeting of the Dawn" (reproduction), 2 pages, 12 copies
        "Greeting of the Dawn" (reproduction), 1 page, 2 copies
      - Songs, single copies (cont.) (Oversize 5)
        "Heat of the Plains" (reproduction), 4 pages, 2 copies
        "Hymn to Evening" (reproduction), 2 pages, 13 copies
        "Hymn to Evening" (reproduction), 1 page
        "Interlude" (reproduction), 1 page
        "Jeremiah" (reproduction), 5 pages, 3 copies
        "Jeremiah" (reproduction), 3 pages, 3 copies
        "Jeremiah" (reproduction), 1 page
        "The Last Train" (reproduction), 8 pages, 12 copies
        "The Last Train" (reproduction), 4 pages
        "The Last Train" (reproduction), 3 pages
        "Lou" (reproduction), 8 pages
        "Lou" (reproduction), 6 pages
        "Lou" (reproduction), 4 pages, 2 copies
        "Lou" (reproduction), 1 page, 3 copies
        "Lou" (reproduction), 1 page, 2 copies
        "Lou" (reproduction), 2 pages, 3 copies
        "Lou and Corrie" (reproduction), 12 pages
        "Lou and Corrie" (reproduction), 1 page
        "Lou's Discourse" (reproduction), 2 pages, 2 copies
        "Lou's Song" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "Lou's Song" (reproduction), 1 page
        "Love O'Clock" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "Love O'Clock" (reproduction), 1 page, 2 copies
        "Mom" (reproduction), 1 page, 4 copies
        "Mom and Corrie", 3 pages
        "Mom and Pop" (reproduction), 3 pages, 4 copies
        "Mom's Rebuke" (reproduction), 3 pages, 2 copies
        "Morning After the Rain" (reproduction), 4 pages, 2 copies
        "Neighbor Man" (reproduction), 3 pages, 2 copies
        "Night-time Music" (reproduction), 4 pages, 2 copies
        "Noon Heat" (reproduction), 1 page, 16 copies
      - Songs, single copies (cont.) (Oversize 6)
        "Pop's Greeting" (reproduction), 3 pages, 4 copies
        "Pop's Greeting" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "Pop's Sermon" (reproduction), 5 pages, 3 copies
        "Pop's Sermon" (reproduction), 9 pages
        "Pop's Sermon" (reproduction), 4 pages, 5 copies
        "Pop's Sermon" (reproduction), 3 pages, 4 copies
        "Pop's Sermon" (reproduction), 1 page, 13 copies
        "Pop's Sermon" (reproduction), 1 page, 6 copies
        "Prelude to the Fight" (reproduction), 3 pages, 4 copies
        "Rain Jubilation" (reproduction), 3 pages, 13 copies
        "Rain Jubilee" (reproduction), 3 pages, 3 copies
        "The Reverind" (reproduction), 2 pages, 2 copies
        "Return of the Neighbors" (reproduction), 1 page
        "Sequel to Hymn" (reproduction), 1 page
        "Shirley's Tap Dance" (reproduction), 4 pages
        "Song of Flowers" (reproduction), 4 pages
        "Song of Flowers" (reproduction), 1 page, 3 copies
        "Summing Up" (reproduction), 3 pages, 12 copies
        "Summing Up" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "Tough Cookie" (reproduction), 8 pages, 3 copies
        "Tough Cookie" (reproduction), 5 pages
        "Tough Cookie" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "Tree Song" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "Twenty Miles" (original & reproduction), 2 pages, 3 copies
        "Twenty Miles" (reproduction), 1 page, 6 copies
        "The Way It Is In Town" (reproduction), 3 pages, 2 copies
        "With the Mockingbird" (reproduction), 1 page
        "Wizard Oil" (original), 2 pages
      - Miscellaneous
        - Scores (Oversize 7)
          1 p. Lyric, "Tree" Notes, no score 1 p. (holograph), 2 pages
          3 miscellaneous sheets (original), 3 pages
          IV "Pop's Greeting" (original), 2 pages
          "Mom" (original ), 2 pages
          XI "Various People" (original), 3 pages
          XXI Duet, "Lou and Corrie" (original), 1 page
          IX "Heat of the Plains" (original), 4 pages
          XIII "Night-time Music" (original), 4 pages
          "XXVIIa" (original), 1 page
          XXII "The Revrind" (original), 7 pages
          X "Tough Cookie" (original), 14 pages
          XV "The Rain After the Drought" (original), 3 pages
          XXIII "Of the Stars and the Moon" (original), 2 pages
          1 Miscellaneous Half-sheet (original), 1 page
          XX "Transport Plane" (original), 4 pages
          "Transport Plane" (original), 3 pages
          "Lou and Corrie" (original), 2 pages
          "The Idling Windmill" (original), 2 pages
          "Lou and Corrie" (original), 9 pages
          "Mom and Pop" (original), 10 pages
          "The Jeremiah" (original), 1 page
          2 Miscellaneous Sheets (original), 2 pages
          I "Lou and Corrie" (original), 1 page
          V "The Jeremiah and Pop's Sermon" (original), 7 pages
          XIV "The Fight" (original), 9 pages
          "Prelude" (original), 1 page
          "Mom and Corrie/ (original), 1 page
          Misc. unrecorded
        - Old manuscripts (Oversize 7)
          I "Lou" (original), 3 pages
          "Love O'Clock" (original), 3 pages
          "Twenty Miles" No. It (original), 3 pages
          "Pop's Greeting" (original), 4 pages
          "Mom" 1 (original), 5 pages
          "The Last Train" (original), 6 pages
          "Various People" (original), 4 pages
          "Tough People" (original, "Tough Cookie"), 2 pages
          "Jeremiah" (original), 1 pages
          "Stand By Thee..." 10 A, B, C, D (original), 7 pages
          XIV "The Fight"'(original), 2 pages
          "Chewing Gum Island" (original), 3 pages
          "16a-3" (original), 1 pages
          "Chorus" (original), 1 pages
          "Pop" (original), 1 pages
          "Windmill" (original), 9 pages
          "Transport Plane" (original), 5 pages
          "Vamp for Froggie" (original), 1 pages
          "Frog Went A Courtin'" (original), 8 pages
          XVIIIa "Sequel to Hymn" (original), 2 pages
          "Recitative Blues and Arioso" (original), 9 pages
          XX "The Reverind" (original), 4 pages
          "The Vamoose" (original), 3 pages
          XXIII "An Easy Trot" (original), 4 pages
          "Rain After the Drought" (original), 4 pages
          4 "Twenty Miles"(original)8 pages
          B "Chewing Gum Island" (original), 4 pages
        - Old manuscripts (cont.) (Oversize 7)
          "Pop's Greeting" et al. (original), 20 pages
        - Sketches (Oversize 7)
          "Night-time Music" et al. (original), 73 pages
        - Sketches (cont.) (Oversize 7)
          "Notes to a Lamp on the Plains" (original), 149 pages
  - General music scores
    - Cello and piano
      - "Sonata for Cello and Piano" parts 2-4 (original), 16 pages (Oversize 7)
    - Choral
      - The Animals' Christmas Oratorio, to a text by Manuel Komroff, folio (Oversize 7)
        "The Butterfly and the Ant" et al. (reproduction), 21 pages
        "The Skunk" et al. (reproduction), 14 pages
        Overture (reproduction), 18 pages
      - The Animals' Christmas Oratorio, to a text by Manuel Komroff, single songs (Oversize 7)
        "The Butterfly and the Ant" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "The Butterfly and the Ant" (reproduction), 6 pages
        "Conclusion" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "The Cow and the Dogs" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "The Cozy Pig" (reproduction), 2 pages, 2 copies
        "Digging the Well" (reproduction), 1 page
        "The Hyena and the Cricket" (reproduction), 2 pages, 3 copies
        "The Lark and the Jay" (reproduction), 6 pages
        "The Lark and the Jay" (reproduction), 3 pages, 2 copies
        "The Lark and the Jay" (reproduction), 1 page, 2 copies
        "The Lion and the Sheep" (reproduction), 6 pages
        "The Lion and the Sheep" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "Pilgrim Hymn" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "The Praying Mantis" (reproduction), 6 pages, 2 copies
        "Preface" (reproduction), 2 pages, 2 copies
        "The Robin and the Gila Monster" (reproduction), 2 pages
        "The Secretary-Bird" (reproduction), 3 pages, 3 copies
      - The Animals' Christmas Oratorio, to a text by Manuel Komroff, single songs (Oversize 7)
        "The Secretary-Bird" (reproduction), 1 page
        "The Skunk" (reproduction), 1 page
        Untitled (reproduction), 4 pages
      - Ecclesiastes Cantata (Oversize 7)
        Original, 79 pages
      - General choral numbers, folio (Oversize 8)